Cornelius W. Wickersham Papers
Cornelius W. Wickersham Papers
1912-1969
Wickersham, Cornelius W. (Cornelius Wendell), 1884-
15.5 linear feet
Papers of the military officer and lawyer. Collection contains legal material (includes papers concerning Interstate Commerce Commission, 1931; various cases involving commerce and transportation including railroads, 1929-39), military files (photographs and papers), and public service material (topics include education and Nassau County Bridge Authority).
148753
Biographical History
Brigadier General Cornelius Wendell Wickersham (1884-1968) was an American lawyer and military officer; he practiced law for more than forty years, and his military career stretched from the Mexicon Border skirmish of 1916 to World War II and after.
Wickersham graduated from Harvard University in 1906 and received his law degree, also from Harvard, in 1909. In 1914 he joined the firm of Cadwalader, Wickersham and Taft, founded in 1792 and today the oldest continuously-operating law firm in New York City (his father George Woodward Wickersham, an anti-trust attorney, had also been with the firm). Apart from absences for military duty, Wickersham continued to practice law for more than sixty years, eventually rising to the position of senior partner. His work included trusts, estates, and corporate reorganization and recapitalization. He was president of the Joint Conference on Legal Education in New York (1932-1940 and 1954-1958) and counsel for the Grand Jury Association of New York County. He also served on the Board of Regents for the state of New York (1953-1955).
Wickersham's military career began in 1915 when he enlisted in the New York Cavalry. From 1916-1918 he served on the U.S.-Mexican border with the 12th New York Infantry. During World War I he was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel and during World War II to Brigadier General. Among his many appointments, he was the first commandant and director of the School of Military Government, established in 1942 at the University of Virginia; Chief of the European Allied Contact Section, serving at Eisenhower's headquarters; and head of U.S. Group Control Council, Germany (USGCC). He served with distinction, receiving the Distinguished Service Medal (twice), the Legion of Merit, the Legion of Honor, Commander of the Order of the British Empire, and the Medal of Verdun, among other honors.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Cornelius W. Wickersham Papers consist of legal, military, public service, education, and personal papers.
Legal material consists of books, briefs, articles, material about specific cases, and other documents relating to Wickersham's lengthy legal career.
Military material subject files span more than three decades, ranging from the Mexican Border incident of 1916 and World War I to World War II and the Army School of Military Government.
The majority of Public service material relates to Wickersham's involvement with the Nassau County Bridge Authority; other topics include civil defense and the American Legion, of which Wickersham was a founding member.
Wickersham's Service to education primarily involves Nassau Community College and his term on the New York Board of Regents. Included here are minutes, a yearbook, policy and procedures manuals, annual reports, budgets, among other things.
Personal papers contains awards, certificates, degrees, honors, medals, photographs, and other types of memorabilia. Of note here are letters from General John J. Pershing and correspondence with Harry Truman and Dwight and Mamie Eisenhower.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material within each series is in no particular order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; New York State; Wickersham, Cornelius W. (Cornelius Wendell), 1884-; Interstate Commerce Commission.; Nassau Community College.; Nassau County Bridge Authority.; University of the State of New York. -- Board of Regents.; Actions and defenses -- Cases.; Lawyers -- United States.; Military history, Modern -- 20th century.; Railroad law -- United States.; Railroads -- Finance -- Law and legislation.; Stamp collecting.; Transportation -- Law and legislation -- United States.; United States -- Armed Forces -- Officers.; Awards.; Briefs (legal documents); Budgets.; Correspondence.; Decorations (honor); Photographs.; School yearbooks.; Lawyers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Legal material
  - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Clark Tread vs. Commissioner of Internal Revenue, 1937 (Box 1)
  - United States vs. the Sugar Institute, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Empre State Inc., 1950; brief (Box 1)
  - Vermont stockholder resolutions, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Legal Book, Wickersham, undated (Box 1)
  - Stock Without Par Value, Wickersham, undated (Box 1)
  - Central Vermont reorganization, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Records, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Plaque, regarding the Constitution, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Canadian National Railway vs. Central Vermont Railway, undated; 8 volumes (Box 2)
  - Goodyear Tire and Rubber, 1927; papers re: shareholder litigation (Box 2)
  - Conveyance distribution and accounting, 1930; 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - New company, 1929-1930; 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Foreclosure and sale, Vermont, 1929; 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Reorganization, stockholders, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Old mortgage, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Organization directors, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Movie cases, 1930; 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - Goodyear case, 1927; 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Records, 1936; 4 volumes (Box 4)
  - Suit in Southern District of New York, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Pleading in Vermont, 1928 (Box 4)
  - Suit in Massachusetts, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Suit in Connecticut, 1929 (Box 4)
  - New York State Bar Association, portfolio (Box 5)
  - The International Bar, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Briefs, Wickersham, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Czarnikow-Rionda Company vs. Federal Sugar Refining Company, 1925; brief (Box 5)
  - Central Vermont Railway, Inc., undated; 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Grand Trunk Railway vs. H.W. Nelson, Inc., 1939; brief summary (Box 5)
  - Grand Trunk Railway vs. H.W. Nelson, Inc., 1939; brief testimony (Box 5)
  - Bar Association, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - American Law Institute, undated (Box 6)
  - Books, articles, broadcasts, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Select Committee, U.S. Senate, undated (Box 6)
- Military material
  - Photo album, undated; 3 volumes (Box 7)
  - Roster of retired officers of 1st Army, undated (Box 7)
  - Mexican Border War and World War I, undated (Box 7)
  - Three-Star General's flag, undated (Box 7)
  - World War II and thereafter, 1940-1948; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - World War II and thereafter, 1948-1968; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Army School of Military Government, undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
- Public service
  - Civil defense, undated (Box 8)
  - American Legion, undated (Box 8)
  - Grant Monument Association, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, correspondence, printed material (Box 8)
  - Nassau County Bridge Authority, undated; 4 portfolios, 1 envelope (Box 9)
- Education
  - Regents Minutes, Wickersham, undated; 2 volumes (Box 10)
  - Nassau Community College minutes, 1960-1964; 8 volumes (Box 10)
  - Nassau College Yearbook, 1964 (Box 11)
  - Methods and procedures manuals, 1963-1965; 3 volumes (Box 11)
  - Budget estimates, Nassau Community College, 1963; 1965; 2 volumes (Box 11)
  - Annual reports, 1959-1963; 3 volumes (Box 11)
  - Nassau Community College, undated; 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Board of Regents, undated; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - College pamphlets, undated; 3 folders (Box 12)
- Personal
  - Committees and associations
    - Reserve Officers Association, undated (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12)
  - Social life
    - Family, undated (Box 12)
  - Hobbies
    - Outdoors, natural history, ornithology, music, undated (Box 12)
    - Philately, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Literature and music, undated (Box 12)
    - The Early Stamps of Venezuela, Wickersham, undated (Box 12)
  - Memorabilia
    - Photographs, 1954; 1960,; undated; includes Wickersham with Dewey (1954) and President Lyndon Johnson (1964) (Oversize 1)
    - Certificate of Regents, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Telegrams, miscellaneous, undated (Oversize 1)
    - U.S. Customs appeals certificates, 1914 (Oversize 2)
    - Attorney certificates, 1912; 1927 (Oversize 2)
    - Appellate Division certificate, 1922 (Oversize 2)
    - Avril Paulson, autograph, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Reserves certificate, 1948 (Oversize 2)
    - Army certficates, 1916; 1923,; 1928 (Oversize 2)
    - Pershing, J. J., 1923; letter from (Oversize 2)
    - French Army award, 1918 (Oversize 2)
    - Veterans award, 1922 (Oversize 2)
    - National Guard certificate, 1916 (Oversize 2)
    - Farrington, P., 1964; letter from (Oversize 2)
    - Bachelor's degree (B.A.) from Massachusetts, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Cum Laude award, undated (Oversize 2)
    - District Court certificate, 1911 (Oversize 2)
    - New Jersey Attorney certificate, 1913 (Oversize 2)
    - Legion of Honor, 1919 (Oversize 2)
    - Army Citation, 1918 (Oversize 2)
    - British Army Award, 1946 (Oversize 2)
    - Distinguished Service Medal, 1945 (Oversize 2)
    - Certificate elections, 1953 (Oversize 2)
    - Citation from Britain, 1945 (Oversize 2)
    - New York State Award, 1948 (Oversize 2)
    - Photographs, black and white, 1960; 2 items (Oversize 2)
    - Awards to Mr. Taft, from Japan, 1929 (Oversize 2)
    - Distinguished Service Medal, 1918 (Oversize 2)
    - Order of the Legion of Honor, 1929; 1946 (Oversize 2)
    - Regents Certificate, 1955 (Oversize 2)
    - Law degree (J.D.), 1918 (Oversize 2)